A Guide to the J. Paxton Marshall Papers, 1965-1999
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
J. Paxton Marshall Papers, 1967-1996
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Marshall, J. Paxton, 1922-2000
Ms2012-074
1 Cubic Feet 1 box
The J. Paxton Marshall Papers collection contains papers, reports and publications on land use issues in Virginia and surrounding states, as well as a small amount of biographical material. The documents included relate to Marshall's tenure in the Department of Agricultural and Applied Economics at Virginia Tech (1967-1995), as well as his work with various committees and as a technical representative for the General Assembly of Virginia.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The J. Paxton Marshall Papers were donated to Special Collections in November 2001.
Biographical Information
J. Paxton Marshall was born in Akron, Ohio on July 31, 1922. He attended the University of Kentucky as an undergraduate, and pursued his M.A. and PhD. at Michigan State University. He began his teaching career in 1961, first at the University of Maryland (1961-1964) and then moving on to Virginia Tech. He was a faculty member in the Department of Agricultural and Applied Economics for nearly 30 years (1967-1995). Over the course of his career, Marshall participated on numerous regional and national committees, most notably: Tobacco Marking Cost Study Committee (1989-1995), American Agricultural Economics Association Professional Activities Committee (1976-1978), Southern Extension Public Affairs Committee (1967-1987), and National Public Policy Education Committee (1962-1987). Marshall also served as a Technical Representative for the General Assembly of Virginia. Upon his retirement in 1995 Marshall was granted the title of Professor Emeritus by the Board of Visitors of Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. He died June 16, 2000.
Scope and Contents
The J. Paxton Marshall Papers collection contains papers, reports and publications on land use issues (primarily in Virginia), as well as a small amount of biographical materials. The documents included relate to Marshall's tenure in the Department of Agricultural and Applied Economics at Virginia Tech (1967-1995), as well as his work with regional and national committees, and as a technical representative for the General Assembly of Virginia.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Faculty; University Archives; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Contents List
- Curriculum Vitae of J. Paxton Marshall, January 1, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- "Materials," an incomplete listing of publications by J. Paxton Marshall included in the collection, 1966-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence with Dr. Wybe Kroontje, Regarding Campus Unrest at VPI, June 4, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence with Mr. Jack A. Wilson, regarding Regulation 401 KAR 5:008E. Swine Feeding Operations, November 24, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Commentary on John Marshall: Definer of a Nation, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence with The Library of Virginia, regarding the portrait of Thomas Marshall, March 17, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence regarding University of Kentucky's national rankings, October 5, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Land: Issues and Problems, produced by Cooperative Extension Service, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Land: Issues and Problems, produced by Cooperative Extension Service, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, 1980-1996 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "National Farmers Organization -- National Arm Twisters?," November 1, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "Locating Development Characteristics Among the Counties of Maryland," prepared for the Maryland Extension Service Community Development Workshop, February 23-25, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "A Housing Authority for Migrant Labor Camp?," November 14, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "A Shipload of Doomed Men," reproduced from Harper's Magazine, January 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "United States Department of Agriculture, Consumer and Marketing Service, Docket No. A0-365 -- Handling of Flue-Cured Tobacco," March 29, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "Policy In the Flue-Cured Tobacco Industry," April 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "The Right of Joining -- P. L. 90-288," May 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "What Research Shows About the Effectiveness of Informal Education in Urban Areas," May 28, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "Seventeen Proposed Peanut Programs Studied by Grower Representatives: A Review", June 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Cooperative Extension Service, VPI, Resource Development, Newsletter, Nos. 23 and 24, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "In the Thirties, We Were Prisoners of Our Illusions, Are We Prisoners in the Sixties?," September 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "Receive the Sanction," October 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "A Report to The Rural Affairs Study Commission," November 13, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "Table -- Public Assistance: Federal, and state, and local payment and administrative costs for public assistant 1935-66," January 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence with Extension Agents concerning the National Farmers Organization, January 7, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "1969 Food Grain Program," February 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "Outlook in Agricultural Policy," presented to the 24th Annual Virginia Bankers Farm Credit Conference, March 3, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Land Use-Value Assessment, article by A. Travis Poole, Jr., Summer 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "A Heuristic Analysis of Agricultural Policy Influences Upon People -- The Flue-Cured Tobacco Program in Retrospect," 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Commentary on "Campus Riots and the U.S. Government," shared with VPI Extension Staff, August 29, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "Table: Tobacco sales charges based on data from a sample of farmer warehouse sales tickets, 1968 sales season, flue-cured and barley," September 19,1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "Urban Design and National Policy for Urban Growth," pamphlet produced by the American Institute of Architects, October 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "Analysis of Current National Welfare Program Alternatives," presented before the National Agricultural Policy Committee, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "1970 Session of the General Assembly," 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "The Quality of Living in Rural Virginia," 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Burley and Flue-Cured Tobacco: Report of the Commission to Study Matters Relating To Flue-Cured and Burley Tobacco," January 7, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Pursuant to F.R. Docket 69-14712, Submitted relative to Type 31 (Burley) Tobacco," January 9, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Senate Bill No. 93," January 19, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Problems with the Old Welfare Programs and Some New Proposals," talk given at the National Agricultural Outlook Conference, February 19, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "1971 Farm Bill Options Exist," prepared for publication in Virginia Agricultural Economics, March 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Virginia Agriculture in the '70's," revised edition of a paper presented at the 25th Annual Virginia Bankers Farm Credit Conference, March 9, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Burley Tobacco Soil Bank Programs," March 18, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Virginia Agricultural Economics," January - March 1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Voting and Elections in Virginia: A 4-H Citizenship Program Resource, May 1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Commentary on "Student Unrest: Sources and Consequences," "Heaven is a Lonely Place," and "Campus Riots and the U.S. Government," shared with VPI Extension Staff, May 15, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "New approaches and Alternative Plans for Resource Management," presented before the TVA Project Update Conference, May 31, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- United States Department of Agriculture, Agricultural Stabilization and Conservation Services, F.R. Docket 70-5463: Proposed Rule Making Flue-Cured Tobacco, June 5, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "Amending Virginia's Constitution: Questions and Answer," September 1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Our Poor Neighbors: What are we doing to help? What could we do?, September 1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Commentary on "The Lessons of Isla Vista," shared with VPI Extension Staff, October 1, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "Manpower Productivity - Who's Responsibility?" presented before the Agribusiness Conference, November 23, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "An article on the Agricultural Act of 1970," shared with Agricultural and Farm Management Agents, December 18, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "Assessment of Agricultural, Horticultural, Forest and Open Space Lands As Provided in House Bill 99," October 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "Boards of Assessors and Boards of Equalization Study Report," December 3, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- The Flue-Cured Tobacco Farmer, December 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "Problems and Alternatives with Collective Marketing Approaches," presented before the Workshop on Pricing Agriculture, January 5-7, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Agricultural Economics Research Report: Title Examination in Virginia, July 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "Zoning in the Long-Run," presented before the Extension Division In-Service Training Session on Land-Use Planning, January 29-31, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "Virginia Housing: Some Items," prepared for presentation before the Extension Division In-Service Training Session 'Human Needs in Housing', April 19, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "Some Questions and Answers on a Proposed Zoning Ordinance for Warren County," April 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "Use-Value Assessment Legislation, as Amended," June 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "Health and Your Community: A Problem in Community Organization," prepared for Family Resources Conference, July 17-19 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Minutes of Southern Public Affairs Committee Meeting, September 20, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "Use-Value Assessment in Virginia: Some Questions and Answers," October 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "The Alternative Forms of County Government in Virginia," November 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "Determining Locations for Rural Medical Clinics: A Model and Its Use," Southern Journal of Agricultural Economics, December 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "The Peanut Program: Some Issues, Some Choices," presented at the Virginia-North Carolina Peanut Research Review, December 17-18 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Virginia Agricultural Economics, newsletter, Nos. 245, 254-264, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Progressive Farmer's Peanut Profit Guide, February 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- "You Are Both In and Of Your Community: You're Important!" prepared for presentation to Southeast Virginia Extension Technician Conference, April 25, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Land-Use Issues: Proceedings of a Conference, November 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- "Health Education Spans Outreach Clinics: A Concept to Consider," Health Education Monograph, vol. 3., no. 1, Spring 1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Papers on Agricultural Policy, February 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- 1978 Forum on the Future of Virginia Agriculture: Papers on Energy Policy, May 1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Current Land And Water Resources Issues in Virginia: Proceeds of a Conference, September 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- "Provisions of the Current Tobacco Program," from Tobacco Marketing Policy Alternatives, September 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- The Virginia Assembly on Land Use Policies: Issues for the Commonwealth: Final Statement, June 18-20, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Conference on the Reclamation of Surface-Mined Land by use of Grasses, Legumes, and Forest Trees, pamphlet, May 9, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Land Use and The Cheapeake Bay, pamphlet, May 15-17, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- The Regional Assemblies of the Virginia Assembly on Future Policy for Elementary and Secondary Education in the Commonwealth, pamphlet, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- A Series of Five Regional Conferences on Agricultural Policy: Issues in the 1985 Farm Bill, pamphlet, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- "Information about the Virginia Rural Leadership Development Program," pamphlet, February 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- "Questions and Answers to Provide More Information About the Virginia Rural Leadership Development Program," November 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Restructuring Policy for Agriculture: Some Alternatives, Papers from a Symposium, May 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- The Virginia Assembly On Policy for Elementary and Secondary Education in Virginia: Issues for the Commonwealth, June 1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- "Issues in Tobacco Policy: A Collapsed Cartel, Decreasing Demand, Excess Supply And A No-Net-Cost Program," 1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Papers on Issues in Agricultural Trade Policy: The United States, Japan, and the European Communities, September 1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Procedure Employed to Determine Use-Value of Agricultural Land in Virginia with Estimated Use-Values for 77 Jurisdictions Authorizing Use-Value Taxation, September 1984 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Papers on Issues in Policy for Agriculture: The 1985 Farm Bill, December 1984 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Reluctant Ratifiers: Virginia Considers the Federal Constitution, program from an exhibition hosted by The Virginia Historical Society, June 2 - December 15, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Land Use and the Chesapeake Bay, manuscript draft, December 1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- "The Near-Perfect Information Tobacco Marketing System: A Proposal," Tobacco Marketing Systems, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- "Focusing the Question 'What is Our Product?' Upon an Institution: The Cooperative Extension," presented at a seminar held at the University of Missouri, May 1994 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Robeson County Rules to Determine If Intensive Livestock Operation is Public Health Nuisance, September 28, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- "Swine Enterpirse Records Average Operations," from Iowa State University, December 14, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Editorial from The Courier-Journal, "Improved Ethics," August 19, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Correspondence regarding proposed floodplain ordinance,Oral Statement of Tom FitzGerald, March 25, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Correspondence regarding Draft Forest Stewardship Legislation, June 30, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Correspondence with Natural Resources and Environmental Protection Cabinet, August 21, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Correspondence regarding the Issuance of State Operational Permit No. 02006072, September 17, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Joint Subcommittee Studying Agricultural and Forestal Districts, July-September 1997 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Kentucky Cagle Water Expansion Project, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Correspondence with Jack A. Wilson, regarding the "New Administrative Regulation 401 KAR 5:008, Swine Feeding Operations," January 22, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Correspondence regarding Senate Bill 18, February 19, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Correspondence with Tom FitzGerald regarding swine waste management, April 10, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Correspondence with Elizabeth U. Natter regarding Poultry Houses, April 15, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Correspondence with Waldon R. Kerns regarding various agricultural issues, August 31, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Large-Scale Hog Operations in Kentucky, manuscript draft, September 1998 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Correspondence with Denise C. Coleman regarding "Draft Unified National Strategy for Animal Feeding Operations," January 19, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Opinion rendered by the Hearing Officer in the Cagles' case, March 8, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Memorandum regarding "Action taken to regulate the poultry industry in Virginia", March 9, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- "The 'Volatile' Tobacco Industry," The Courier-Journal, May 17, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Correspondence with Betsy Bennett regarding 'Bottle Bills', October 2, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- "Extension in a Theoretical Framework," article draft, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- "Proposed Hiking and Bridle Path Developement," n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- "Income Maintenance: Welfare, People and Governments", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- "Use-Value Assessment - What is it?," n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- "Strengthening County Government", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- "Local Government in Montgomery County, Virginia", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- "Local Government in Amherst County, Virginia," n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Watershed Projects and Soil Conservation Districts: A Teaching Guide, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Seven Radio Program Scripts on "Who Will Control U.S. Agriculture", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
- "A Proposed Urban Agricultural Enterprise," n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Agricultural Economics Research Report: Thesis and Dissertation Proposals on Property Taxation, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
- "Model Health Department Regulations Governing Intensive Livestock Operations," n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Selection of 'Property and Coveyances from the Code of Virginia', n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)